黑客们，你好
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn.college的另一个视频
welcome to another pwn College video
今天我们将讨论逆向工程
today we'll be talking about reverse engineering
具体来说，逆向工程是什么
specifically what reverse engineering is
我们开始吧
let's get started
我把我移到这儿
let me move my video over here
我觉得这里不会影响后续展示
I think this is a safe spot for it
在接下来的课程中
for the rest of the lecture
逆向工程是什么呢？
um what is reverse engineering well
要了解逆向工程
to understand reverse engineering
首先让我们了解工程学
first let's understand engineering
具体来说
specifically
常规的软件工程
kind of normal engineering and software development
我讲的是
which I'll talk about in terms of
正向开发
forward engineering here
对吧，工程过程
right the engineering process
在这是创建一个程序的过程 （语气词）
in this context is the creation of a program right
开发程序
and the creation of a program
很直接
is pretty straightforward
想好你要写啥
you figure out what you want to write
写出来
you write it
编译
you compile it
编译可能是
that might be
隐式步骤
an implicit step
因为你的代码可能实际是由
as your code is actually executed by
运行时编译引擎执行
just in time compilation engine
或者其他类似的
and or or things like that
然后你运行它
and then you run it and
这是一种工程
and that's kind of the engineering
流程
you know process
运行可能不是流程的一部分
I guess running it isn't
告诉我过程的一部分
telling me part of the process
重点是
but the point is
这个过程
the process is kind of
近似 右边的步骤
approximated on the right here
在那里
there
有一堆步骤
with a bunch of steps right
从设计开始
you you start with the design
你编写代码，编译，还有一些
you code you compile and then there's some
你知道
you know
挫折在那里，然后最终事情成功了
frustration there and then eventually things work
好吧
all right um
the
关于逆向工程需要了解的是
thing to understand about reverse engineering
这个过程中的每个环节都
is that at every point in this process
有信息丢失
information is lost
（语气词）逆向工程要
right and reverse engineering is the
重新获取这些丢失的信息
concept of getting that information back
这是非常复杂的。让我们
which is very non trivial so let's
过一遍
roll through
每一步什么样的信息可能会丢失
you know what kind of information might be lost at
every step right first
在设计和
between design and
代码创建过程中大量信息丢失
the creation of code a lot of information is lost
如：意图
this has to do with intent
这个程序想要做什么
right what was this program supposed to do
你经常会看到一些代码
oftentimes you look at some code even
甚至是你自己写的
yourself has written
可能在一个学期，一年或十年前
a semester or a year or a decade ago
你会觉得
and you think what
我tm当时在想啥，或者
was I thinking or sometimes as a bonus you think
这代码tmd谁写的
who the heck wrote this code
对吧，结果就是你自己写的
right and turns out it was you right
信息会丢的更多，
and then things get worse when you
等到编译和汇编时
get to that kind of compiling and assembling step
你把代码传给编译器
you take your code you pass it through your compiler
编译器立马会
and your compiler immediately
去掉所有注释
strips out all of the comments
这些注释很有用
right those comments are useful
这些注释有助于理解
those comments are useful to understand the
您在编写代码时的意图
your intent when writing the code
以及代码的功能
and the functionality of the code
但他们现在已经没了
but they're gone now
从编译步骤开始
right just from the compilation step
你会丢失变量名
you lose variable names
我来演示一下
and I'll show a demo
变量就变成了内存地址
variables just become memory locations right and then
大量语义知识丢失了
a lot of semantic knowledge is lost
你经常会丢失函数名
you often lose function names
您将丢失所有类型信息
you lose all type information
有时候编译器可能会优化
and sometimes the compiler might optimize out
一个完整的算法
an entire algorithm
你有一些很好的
right so you had some very well
指定的数学运算
specified mathematical operation
编译器说哦
and the compiler says oh
没问题，我知道一个更快的方法
no problem I know a faster way to do this
然后把你指定的算法替换掉
replace it with a faster way
如果你对代码进行逆向工程
if you're reverse engineering that code
会发现无法理解作者的意图了
it might no longer make sense right so
逆向工程要解决一个问题
reverse engineering is kind of the question of you know
我们怎么把这些丢失信息都找回来
how do we get all of this information back
从最终产品
from the final product
从可执行文件
from the executable
二进制代码
the binary code
到目前为止，在这门课上我们一直在处理
until now in this course we've been dealing with
源代码，从这个模块开始我们要接触
source code this module really represents our jump into
二进制代码了
binary code
或者说我们之前做题时一直能得到源码
or rather we've been dealing a source code
in the practice problems
对，你有源代码
right you always have gotten source code now
从现在开始我们不会在拿到
from this point on we will no longer get
源代码了
that source code
好吧
all right
所以
so
让我们来看看一些正向开发的工具
let's look at some forward engineering tools
来
to kind of
帮助理解逆向工程
contextualize the reverse engineering process
我们会了解IDE, 我使用Vim
we're going to look at an IDE I use Vim
有些人使用真正的IDE，但是
some people use a Real IDE but
我们不会在这里这么做
we will not be doing that here
然后我们将讨论编译后
and then we will look at the compilation
还留下的东西
process what it kind of leaves behind
什么信息还在
what what information is still there
然后
and then
当我们剥夺了这些信息会发生什么
what happens when we strip that information away
好，让我们
alright let's
探个究竟
check this out
所以我有我的
so I have my um
它（录频工具）选错了终端
it picked up the wrong terminal
等一下，我来解决这个问题
hold on a second let me fix this
好了，我们回来
all right we're back
我们不得不和OBS做点斗争
we had to fight with OBS a little bit to
来显示正确的窗口，但它现在好了
get the right window to display but it's here now
好吧
okay
我们在终端上
so we're on the terminal
我写了一个hello world程序
of course I wrote a hello world program
这是一个简单的程序，2个函数
this is a simple program 2 functions
还有一个变量名
and a variable name
它的变量名为my name
right so it has this variable name of my name
程序从标准输入接收一个最长1000
it reads in up to 1000
个字符的字符串到my_name数组中
character along string into that
然后它调用 say_hello 函数
then it calls say hello
参数为my_name，该函数输出 hello blabla
with the name and it just says hello
如果你编译它
right so if you compile it
然后运行它
and run it
就是这样
there it is
非常酷的hello world程序
very cool hello world program all right
我们来看一条信息
so let's see one information
就在这里，有几件条信息
is here right there there's a couple things
一个是
one is
变量my_name
this variable my name
另一个是这个变量的长度
another one is the length of this vary
uhh，数组的长度
the length of the array
它是一个字符数组
and it's a character array
因为它是由一串字符组成
the fact that it's an array of characters
另一个信息是
another
这个函数把
piece of information is that this function takes
这个字符数组作为输入参数
this array of characters as input
另一个是
and another one is
这个函数名say hello
that this functions named say hello
好吧
okay
我来给你们看看每一步都丢失了什么
and I'm gonna go through and show you what is lost
at every step
让我们从
so let's start with
编译
compilation
实际上，不是编译
actually rather than compilation let's start
让我在这里加一个注释
let me add a comment here
让我们从
let's start with
预处理开始
with the pre processing
这
this
是一个变量用来保存我的名字
is a variable to hold my name
好的，这里有了一个注释
okay so here's a comment
编译过程中发生的第一件事
the first thing that happens in the compilation process
我不记得对应的
and I don't remember that
GCC命令参数了（-E）
GCC flags are
gcc -E 的实现是调用cpp，所以这里直接调cpp了
involved as directly as the c pre processor runs
c预处理器
the c pre processor
处理所有的include语句
handles all the include statements
和
and
扩展宏等等
expands macros and so forth
并且它会删除注释
and it removes comments
这是实际被编译的代码
so this is the code that actually gets compiled
如果我把所有东西都包括进去的话
if I properly had included everything
我本应该包括
I should have included
stdio . h
stdio.h
所以现在
so now that if
当我编译它时，我们没有得到任何警告
when I compile it we don't get any warnings
c预处理程序实际上拷贝
the c pre processor will actually include
stdio . h。这是全部的内容
stdio.h. this is all of the stuff
这些都是stdio。h
this is all the stuff that is an stdio.h
让我用less看看
let me less through this
这是所有include的东西
so here's all of the stuff that's included
我的代码在最下面
and my actual code is right at the bottom there
C预处理器
and the C pre processor
删除了我的注释
removed my comment
好了
there you have it
好的，那么
alright so then
把输出重定向到
so this gets into
hello-preprocessed
hello pre processed
点c
dot c
然后有一个
and then there is a
汇编步骤（口误）
assembling step
我们的C代码，不好意思，是编译步骤
right so our our C code or sorry a compilation step
我们的C代码被编译成
our C code is compiled
汇编代码
into assembly code
我最近才发现
and I recently found out
内个
that
我可以让GCC生成英特尔
I can have GCC actually generate Intel
语法风格的汇编代码
syntax assembly which is going to be much better
我们用预处理的hello
so we take the pre processed hello
然后我们对它进行汇编（口误）
and then we assemble it
现在我们把hello-preprocess.
and now we have hello pre process dot
哦，抱歉，我们把它编译成汇编代码
oh sorry we compile it into a assembly code
这就是最终结果
and this is the end result
那么这里发生了什么
so what happened here
这是我们的
this is now our
将要使用的汇编代码
the assembly code that will be
汇编以生成C代码（口误，应该是机器码）
assembled to generate the C code
这一步我们丢失了什么呢
and what did we lose in this step well
我们失去的一条信息是
one thing we lost is
我们看看main函数
let's go to main
在main这里
here in main
曾经有一个字符数组
there used to be a character array
让我展示一下原始代码
let me show the original source
有一个字符数组
there was a character array
my_name,对吧
with my name right
现在
now
变量名my name没有了
the variable name my name is gone
现在只是一段内存
it is now just a memory
偏移（rbp-1040）在这
reference right here
在栈的某个地方
somewhere on on the stack
我们之后会讲到栈是什么等等
we'll talk about what the stack is later and so forth
但它的名字已经不存在了
but the name of it is gone
我们已经丢失了变量名
we've already we lost variable names here
至少是函数的局部变量
already at least local variables to functions
我们还丢失了所有类型信息
we also lost all the type information
实际上原来这儿是
the fact that it was
1024的大小，现在这儿是1040
1024 in size you see this 1040
有些东西被填充了（内存对齐）
something got padded
或者是
or it's
对函数栈帧中的其他东西进行补偿
compensating for other things in the function frame
我们稍后会讲到函数栈帧的位置
we'll talk about where a function frame is later
在逆向教学模块中
in the module as well
我们丢失了它是一个字符数组的信息
we've lost the fact that it's a character array and
等等
so on
是的，我们已经丢失了很多信息
right so we've already lost quite a lot of information
但至少
but at least the
say_hello（函数名）
say hello
这个字符串还在这里
the string is still there
如果我们完成了编译
well if we finish compiling it
你对它反汇编，还能看到这个say_hello
you can see here if you disassemble the result
say hello字符串仍然在那里
the say hello string is still there
但软件通常不是这样的
but this is not how
软件通常是
software is typically
让我们反编译它
let's decompile it just for
适当的错误
appropriate mistake
就在那儿
it's right there
软件通常不会这样
this is not typically how software is
发布，软件通常也被剥离和
shift typically software is also stripped and
删除任何不必要的元数据，以减小大小
of any unnecessary metadata to reduce the size
如果你看一下hello的大小，然后再strip
if you look at the size of hello and then you'll strip
hello，再看看它的大小
hello look at the size of it again
变小了
smaller nicer
对逆向工程不那么友好了
less open to reverse engineering
现在你再反汇编一下
now if you memory dump it
整个代码段没有信息
the whole text segment has no information for G
能让objdump
for object dump
找到
to figure it
函数在哪儿了
even where functions are
如果我们
and if we
看看字符串
look at strings
是另一件事
which is the other thing
让我们重新编译一下
let's recompile this
查看字符串和原始编译
look at strings and original compilation
寻找我们的say name函数
and look for our say name function
对不起，say hello函数
sorry say hello function
就在这里
it's right here
好吧
okay
如果我们剥掉它
if we strip it
它没了，所以我们失去的越来越多
it's gone right so we lose more and more
随着我们越来越深入地研究
data as we go further and further in to the
正向工程过程
forward engineering process
现在有一件事
now one thing
您可以带着所有这些数据发布二进制文件
you can ship binaries with all of this data
大部分数据还在里面
most of this data still in them
我们可以编译
we can compile
从原来的二进制
from the original binary
用
with
-G参数，它将包括所有的
dash G flag which will include all of the
信息
information on
变量大小的变量名上的所有类型
types on everything on variable names on variable sizes
如果我现在用strings查看hello里的字符串
if I now do strings hello
我的名字
my name
即使变量仍然显示变量名
even the variable still shows up the variable name
但通常
but typically
大部分信息都丢失了
most of this information is lost
这是一个函数的定义
the the definition that this is even a function
必须要恢复
has to be recovered
使用逆向工程工具和
using reverse engineering tools and
以及所有其他丢失的信息
and and all of the other loss information as well
好吧
alright
所以
so
什么是逆向工程过程
what is the reverse engineering process or
逆向工程的过程是
the reverse engineering process is
基本上是反向的
basically going backwards
从可执行文件开始
starting from the executable
而不是从源代码
instead of starting from the source code
或者从设计开始
or starting from the design
甚至更好的
even better
你从可执行文件开始反汇编它
you start from the executable you disassemble it
反编译它
you decompile it
无论是手动还是自动
whether manually or automatically
你用你的直觉做了很多思考来推断
you do a lot of thinking to infer using your intuition
代码背后的原始意图
the original intent behind the code
这并不容易
it is not easy
这是一门艺术
and it is an art
是的，这是一门艺术
right it's an art of
从
putting yourself in the
开发者的角度
mind and the shoes of the developer
试着去理解
and trying to understand
在这个过程中，您通常使用几个工具来完成
typically in this process you use several tools to
提取知识
extract knowledge
然后你把这些知识放在你的大脑里
and then you put this knowledge together in your brain
建立对程序的理解
build up an understanding of the program
在本模块中，我们将学习如何做到这一点
and throughout this module we'll learn how to do that
然后我们来练习一下
and then we'll practice it
请继续关注
stay tuned